<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-noctem-cogitator-witness-protocol-00" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="independent" version="3">
  <front>
    <title>Cogitator Witness Protocol</title>
    <author fullname="noctem-o" surname="noctem-o"/>
    <date year="2026" month="May" day="9"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This draft documents the current Cogitator reference implementation for tamper-evident AI-agent run records. It defines schema versions, commitment boundaries, and witness-root recomputation semantics.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Status</name>
      <t>Draft; reference implementation protocol snapshot.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Schema constants</name>
      <t>Trace schema version is 3, witness manifest schema version is 3, and tool transcript schema version is 4.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Canonicalization</name>
      <t>Witnessed material uses a strict deterministic canonical JSON subset (JCS-style/I-JSON constrained, integer-only witnessed numbers). This draft does not claim full RFC 8785 conformance for all JSON artifacts.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Witness root algorithm</name>
      <t>The authoritative root is computed by a domain-separated BLAKE3 linear chain over canonical witnessed metadata, then per-step agent-trace witness entries, then per-step tool operations ordered by tool_call_idx (including phantom/intercepted entries).</t>
      <t>Manifest file hashes and bundle hash are diagnostic self-consistency values and are not witness-root authority.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Hashing diagnostics</name>
      <t>Artifact hashes and bundle hash in witness manifests are SHA-256 self-consistency diagnostics in the current implementation.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Verification model</name>
      <t>Verification supports bundle self-consistency checks, semantic witness recompute, and anchored comparison when an external expected root is supplied.</t>
      <t>A co-located witness_root.txt is not external anchoring.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Path confinement</name>
      <t>Manifest artifact paths must be bundle-relative. Absolute paths, canonical escapes, and symlink escapes are rejected.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Threat model limits</name>
      <t>The protocol detects post-hoc mutation of committed contents against an expected root and rejects malformed/incomplete transcripts. It does not attest hardware/runtime environment and does not prove occurrence without external anchoring.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
</rfc>
